Helen and Sydney Stringer Correspondence
Helen and Sydney Stringer Correspondence
1943-1989
1943-1945
Stringer, Helen.
2.25 linear ft.
World War II correspondence between Helen Stringer and her husband Sydney, a Captain in the U.S. Army Medical Corps, stationed in North Africa, Italy, France, and Germany.
4795913
Biographical History
Helen Dann Stringer (1909-2007) was a 1931 graduate of Syracuse University, and also graduated from Yale University School of Nursing in 1934. An active member of such organizations as Planned Parenthood and League of Women Voters among others, she also volunteered with her husband on medical relief operations in Malaysia, Vietnam, Tunisia, and Haiti. A published author later in life, she chronicled the life of her grandmother in Millie M.D.: The Story of a Nineteenth Century Woman, 1846-1927 (1992), and published her and her husband's World War II correspondence in Letters of Love and War: A World War II Correspondence (1998).
Dr. Sydney Walter Stringer (1908? - 1978) was a graduate of Cornell University (1929) and of Yale University School of Medicine (1933). During World War II, as a Captain in the U.S. Army Medical Corps, he was stationed in North Africa, Italy, France, and Germany between 1944 and 1945. After World War II, he returned to his gynecology practice which he had started in 1936, and continued there until 1973. He also further served the Army as a medical officer at the Army Reserve Hospital and the Army Reserve Training Center in Liverpool, NY. After retiring, he was known in his later years as a cello player and collector of rare orchids.
[Some information adapted from Helen Dann Stringer's obituary, Syracuse.com]
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Helen and Sydney Stringer Correspondence contains letters written between Helen Dann Stringer and Sydney W. Stringer during Sydney's deployment in Europe in World War II, as well as items written from their children to Sydney, and an edited transcription of the letters from March, 1944 - July, 1945.
Arrangement of the Collection
Arranged alphabetically by type, with correspondence arranged chronologically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Military history; New York State; Science and medicine; Stringer, Helen Dann.; Stringer, Sydney Walter.; United States. -- Army. -- Medical Corps.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Campaigns -- Africa, North.; Syracuse (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 1918-1945.; World War, 1939-1945 -- New York -- Syracuse.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives, American.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Medical care.; Correspondence.; Transcriptions (documents); Pins (jewelry)
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Helen Stringer, 1990.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Children to Sydney, 1944; undated (Box 1)
  - Helen and Sydney, 1943, Jun, Oct; 1944, Jan, Mar-Aug; 14 folders (Box 1)
  - Helen and Sydney, 1944, Sep-Dec; 12 folders (Box 2)
  - Helen and Sydney, 1944; empty envelopes (Box 3)
  - Helen and Sydney, 1945, Jan 1-Apr 13; 10 folders (Box 3)
  - Helen and Sydney, 1945, Apr 14-Jul 30; 11 folders; includes empty envelopes (Box 4)
  - Helen and Sydney, undated; includes fragments; 2 folders (Box 4)
- Memorabilia
  - Miscellaneous, undated; eagle insignia pin and later note by Helen (Box 4)
- Printed Material
  - Prisms, 1989 (Box 5)
    This volume contains an abridged transcription by Helen Stringer of Helen and Sydney's correspondence, Mar 23, 1944 - Jul 12, 1945. The title page is inscribed "To the George Arents Research Library," and signed by Helen Stringer, Jan 23, 1990.